Alvin A. Lawrence Papers 2011.0086
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Alvin A. Lawrence Papers
undated, 1896-1993
2011.0086
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
14.0 Linear feet Two large flat folders, two flat boxes, one .5 archives box and one tube, of drawings, diagrams and photographs of railroad locomotives and cars, almost all belonging to the New Haven Railroad and its predecessor companies.
The papers consist of drawings done by Alvin A. Lawrence of Columbus, Ohio, of locomotives and cars of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its predecessor rairoad lines for publications sponsored by the New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association, particularly for its magazine Shoreliner.
Lawrence, Alvin A.
McDonald, Paul
Scope and Content
The papers consist of drawings by Alvin A. Lawrence of locomotives (steam and electric) and cars (passenger, box, freight, baggage, club, sleeper, etc.) of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and some of its predecessor lines including the Central New England Railway, the Boston & Providence Railroad, and the New York & New England Railroad. The collection also holds company drawings (created by railroad company) and erecting cards, or diagrams, (created by the builders of the locomotives and cars) and other blueprints and drawings from the railroad of its rolling stock, plus a few photographs of the trains. Many of the drawings were done or gathered by Mr. Lawrence for publications of the New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association, particularly its magazine Shoreliner.
Biography
Alvin A. Lawrence was born in Branford, Connecticut, in 1923 and served in the U.S. Navy during World War II. He attended college in Indiana, earning a degree in Aeronautical and Civil Engineering, and spent his career as an engineer, retiring in 1991. He currently lives in Columbus, Ohio, and created the locomotive and car drawings for publications sponsored by the New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The Papers were donated by Alvin A. Lawrence in August 2011.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Diagrams.; Drawings.; Electric Locomotives.; Locomotives.; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Photographs.; Steam locomotives.
- Series I: Drawings of locomotives and cars, undated, 1896-1993
  - Steam locomotives, including those for the New Haven Railroad's following classes: I-1, I-2, U-3, Y-3, and Z-2, the Daniel Nason of the Boston & Providence Railroad, and the Wallingford (locomotive 11) of the Hartford & New Haven Railroad, also includes drawings of the New Haven Railroad electric EF-4, undated (Item 1, Folder 1)
  - Business, pay, funeral, and crew cars (including #3, the Meadow Lark), and an Old Colony Railroad director's car, undated (Item 1, Folder 2)
  - Rail bus diagrams of cars of the New Haven Railroad, Diesels 0906, U35B, and CPA 24-5, and a Class X-6 gas rail bus of the New York, Ontario & Western Railroad, undated (Item 1, Folder 3)
  - Erecting cards for the several classes of New Haven Railroad locomotives, include A-1, B-2, C-3, C-15, C-15-A, G-3, I-1, I-5, K-1, K-2, P-1, T-2, U-3. Also includes blueprints of engine trucks, steam chest cover, valve gear and tenders, 1908-1978 (Item 2, Folder 4)
  - "Bluelines from Linens," including all classes of New Haven Railroad steam locomotives plus the Comet and Besler self-propelled trains, 1971-1975 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Original drawings and posters of many different classes of steam locomotives, 1896-1902 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Painting & Lettering (all equipment excepting steam),", 1951-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Gas rail buses and the M-2 multiple unit car, an Amfleet coach, Providence, Warren & Bristol Railroad interurban, Nantasket Beach Railway open car. Includes the Old Colony Railroad's Plymouth Rock, 1916-1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "Freight & Non-revenue Originals": car types include piggyback, gondola, milk, snow plow, flanger, coke, caboose, transformer, and wreck train. Also includes cars for the New York & New England Railroad, the Old Colony Railroad, and the Central New England Railway, 1922, 1972-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Baggage cars, sleepers (for Fall River Railroad), suburban coaches, 1939, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Direct current equipment" for steam locomotives G-2, G-3, K-1, and T-2, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "Passenger cars," includes dining cars, baggage cars, smokers and multiple unit cars, 1936-1954 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - New York & New England Railroad Express car, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Electric, steam and diesel locomotives, 1942, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Assorted cars -- inspection, crew, paymaster, Pullman, including gas electric and railbuses, 1935, 1987-1990 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Blueprint of a Boston & Albany Railroad double end engine 4-6-6- type, plus miscellaneous New Haven Railroad steam and electric locomotives (galley proofs of drawings for New Haven Railroad Historical and Technical Association diagram books), undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - The New Haven Railroad Historical & Technical Association, Inc.'s 1923 New York, New Haven & Hartford/ Central New England with 1959 New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad characteristics charts, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Fantrip book for "East Wind" and article about Hoosac Tunnel, 1911, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Assorted small drawings (steam and electric), undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Small drawings of passenger cars, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Small drawings of freight cars, including those for the New York & New England Railroad, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Drawing of a EP-1 locomotive, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Large blueprint (elevation) of 4-4-2 type locomotive, 1908 (Item 6)
- Series II: Map, 1932
  - Map: Portions of Hartford & Connecticut Western Railroad operated and not operated, 1932 (Item 6)
- Series III: Photographs of locomotives and cars, undated, 1953-1963
  - "Backwoods Railroads In Print" by Richard Steinheimer, with loose pages, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Five photographs by Paul McDonald of New Haven Railroad trains, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Maybrook Manifest, photograph by Thomas J. McNamara, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 19)